At the moment when the clouds swallow the full moon
구름이 보름달을 삼키는 순간
Is that when he showed up?
그 사람이 나타났을 때인가요?
No
아니요
That's when he ransacked the warehouse
그 때 그는 창고를 샅샅이 뒤졌습니다.
So you really saw it with your own eyes?
그럼 정말 직접 눈으로 보신 건가요?
Of course I saw it
물론 봤지
At the moment when the clouds spit out the moon
구름이 달을 뱉어내는 순간
that person
그 사람
It's a white guy
백인놈이네
It's Lin Juzheng's soul that has been resurrected
부활한 것은 Lin Juzheng의 영혼입니다
What are you talking about?
무슨 말을하는거야?
I heard he has a high nose bridge
콧대가 높다고 들었는데
He can be called the most handsome man in North Korea
그는 북한에서 가장 잘생긴 남자라고 불릴 수 있다
over there
저기
Damn it, that's not even human.
젠장, 그건 인간도 아니잖아.
He is clearly a monster covered with hair.
그는 분명 머리카락으로 뒤덮인 괴물이다.
Isn’t he a Taoist priest who lived to be a hundred years old?
백세까지 산 도사 아닌가?
An old man who lived to be a hundred years old
백세까지 살았던 노인
Who has the strength to distribute thousands of stones of white rice throughout the capital?
수천 개의 백미 돌을 수도 전역에 배포할 힘을 가진 사람은 누구입니까?
so
그래서
Is that thief a handsome man?
그 도둑은 잘 생긴 남자인가요?
Are you planning to rob the widow and get married?
미망인의 물건을 털고 결혼할 계획인가요?
You are really... Don’t pay too much attention to a man’s appearance
너 정말... 남자 외모에 너무 신경쓰지마
They say it's a hairy monster.
털이 많은 괴물이라고 하더라고요.
So powerful that it scares people to death
사람을 죽게 만들 정도로 강력하다.
You people are really
여러분 정말
I told you last night... Auntie
어젯밤에 말했잖아... 이모
I saw our righteous thief with my own eyes
나는 우리의 의로운 도둑을 내 눈으로 보았다
He is Bai Ding
그는 바이딩이다
Much better
훨씬 나아요
Wash your eyes with salt water for three days
3일 동안 소금물로 눈을 씻으세요.
Rinse twice with warm water
따뜻한 물로 두 번 헹궈주세요
Eunjo thank you
은조 고마워요
But uncle
하지만 삼촌
Did you know that eye diseases can cause blurry vision?
안과질환이 시력을 저하시킬 수 있다는 사실을 알고 계셨나요?
pig
돼지
That's right, chicken head
그렇구나, 닭머리
what is that
그게 뭐야?
Is it Chilong?
칠롱인가?
What a ghost
정말 유령이군요
It turns out to be a snakehead
뱀머리로 밝혀지네요
It's a chicken head
닭머리에요
I originally thought that guy Shi San was just bragging.
나는 원래 Shi San이라는 남자가 단지 자랑하고 있다고 생각했습니다.
I didn’t expect that even my eyes were unreliable
내 눈조차 믿을 수 없을 줄은 몰랐어
This is a medicinal material that helps improve jaundice syndrome
황달증후군 개선에 도움을 주는 약재입니다.
He must not have even seen the shadow of the righteous thief.
그는 의로운 도둑의 그림자조차 보지 못했을 것입니다.
Does it make sense that thieves still talk about justice?
도둑들이 아직도 정의에 관해 이야기한다는 것이 말이 됩니까?
do you really think so
너 정말 그렇게 생각하니?
Corrupt officials fill their coffers by exploiting the people
부패한 관료들이 국민을 착취하여 금고를 채우다
Strictly speaking, the property in the warehouse
엄밀히 말하면 창고에 있는 재산은
Originally belonged to the common people
원래는 일반 서민의 소유였으나
So it's not so much shoplifting
그러니 그다지 도둑질은 아니지
It's more like returning the property to its original owner, right?
원래 주인에게 물건을 돌려주는 것과 비슷하죠?
Isn't that true?
그렇지 않나요?
Does Mr. Ti Tiao also support that thief?
Ti Tiao 씨도 그 도둑을 지지합니까?
How could I support thieves?
도둑을 어떻게 지원할 수 있습니까?
Just stating the facts
단지 사실을 기재했을 뿐입니다
Rumors are always mixed in truth, right?
소문에는 항상 진실이 섞여있죠?
So...is that name also fake?
그럼...그 이름도 가짜인가요?
name?
이름?
The people called that person "lucky boy"
사람들은 그 사람을 '행운의 소년'이라고 불렀다.
A companion on the road?
길 위의 동반자?
Ji Tong for short?
줄여서 지통?
Some people also say that it is "a lifeline for people on the streets."
어떤 사람들은 그것이 "거리의 사람들의 생명선"이라고 말하기도 합니다.
What a headache
정말 두통이군요
Various rumors make the case confusing.
다양한 소문이 사건을 혼란스럽게 만듭니다.
I just... You just...
난 그냥... 넌 그냥...
Did you say it was confusing?
혼란스럽다고 했죠?
If the case is confusing, you should come to me.
사건이 혼란스러우면 나에게로 오세요.
It's really mysterious. I heard the news and came here again.
정말 신비롭습니다. 그 소식을 듣고 또 여기로 왔어요.
We meet again, Your Majesty.
다시 만납니다, 폐하.
long time no see
오랜만이네
However
그러나
Tsunasa's laws have turned into a mess. What a big trouble.
츠나사의 법칙은 엉망이 되어버렸습니다. 정말 큰 문제입니다.
Please take a seat
자리에 앉으세요
We're both busy, so we can skip the courtesy.
우리 둘 다 바쁘기 때문에 예의는 건너뛸 수 있습니다.
No need to thank you
고마워할 필요 없어
I lend my wisdom and wisdom to you dull people.
나는 당신에게 둔한 사람들에게 나의 지혜와 지혜를 빌려줍니다.
Not once or twice
한두번도 아니고
Every time I investigate a case, I’m grateful for your help.
사건을 조사할 때마다 여러분의 도움에 감사드립니다.
I'm really grateful, little one
정말 고마워요, 꼬마야.
The thief who stole thousands of stones and rice?
수천 개의 돌과 쌀을 훔친 도둑?
Where are the victims? There are none.
피해자들은 어디에 있나요? 아무것도 없습니다.
It seems that corrupt officials are afraid that their crimes will be exposed
부패한 공직자들은 자신들의 범죄가 드러날 것을 두려워하는 것 같습니다.
I don’t even dare to report to the police anymore.
더 이상 감히 경찰에 신고할 엄두도 나지 않습니다.
It’s not that I don’t dare, it’s that I didn’t report it
감히 못하는 것이 아니라 신고하지 않은 것이다
If it were me, I wouldn't repay it
나였으면 안 갚았을 텐데
why
왜
Someone informed me the night before yesterday
어제 밤에 누가 나한테 알려줬어
He said that he saw Ji Tong in the warehouse of Da Si Jian Mansion
그는 Da Si Jian Mansion 창고에서 Ji Tong을 보았다고 말했습니다.
Yes, we have a servant in the house
응, 집에 하인이 있어
Saw something suspicious
뭔가 수상한 걸 봤어
The warehouse was filled up so quickly?
창고가 이렇게 빨리 채워졌나요?
Da Sijian looks shabby in appearance
Da Si Jian은 외모가 초라해 보입니다.
The fortune is very prosperous
운이 매우 좋아
Not like that
그렇지 않아요
I guess I didn't find the stolen items.
아무래도 도난당한 물건을 찾지 못한 것 같아요.
Yes everything is intact
응 모든 게 멀쩡해
Go in and search Yes
들어가서 검색해 Yes
Found it
찾았다
Looks like a gourd bowl filled with rice
마치 조롱박 그릇에 밥이 가득 들어 있는 것처럼 보이지만
Was this painting left by Ji Tong?
이 그림은 지통이 남긴 그림인가요?
Exactly
정확히
Could it be...
그럴 수도 있지...
Quickly measure the weight
빠르게 체중을 측정하세요.
How much less
얼마나 적게
Pour a bag of rice in
쌀 한 봉지를 부어주세요.
The rice vat should be full
쌀통이 가득 차 있어야 합니다
This is exactly three buckets short
정확히 세 통이 부족해요
So what did Ji Dong really steal?
그렇다면 지동은 과연 무엇을 훔쳤는가?
Only these three buckets of rice
이 쌀 세 통만
Because of this
이 때문에
Most people don’t realize the theft until a long time later
대부분의 사람들은 오랜 시간이 지나서야 도난 사실을 깨닫습니다.
Even if you notice it, there aren’t many of them.
눈치채더라도 그 수가 많지 않습니다.
Naturally, I am too lazy to report it to the official.
당연히 공무원에게 보고하기에는 너무 게으르다.
Have any people claimed to have received things from Jitong?
지통으로부터 물건을 받았다고 주장하는 사람이 있습니까?
Actually not even one
사실 하나도 안됨
He's just a self-obsessed little thief.
그는 단지 자기 집착적인 작은 도둑일 뿐입니다.
People don't even know this
사람들은 이런 것조차 모르죠
There are rumors everywhere that he is a righteous thief
그가 정의로운 도둑이라는 소문이 도처에 널려 있다
Such a painting
그런 그림
Are there any others?
다른 사람도 있나요?
Why did he have to keep these paintings?
왜 그는 이 그림들을 보관해야 했을까?
If you don’t leave the painting, no one will know about it.
그림을 떠나지 않으면 아무도 그 사실을 알 수 없습니다.
That's right
그렇죠
Not making fun of anyone
누구도 놀리지 않음
What else could it be?
또 무엇이 있을까요?
Because this person regards stealing as a way to show off.
왜냐하면 이 사람은 도둑질을 과시하는 방법으로 여기기 때문입니다.
Human beings originally
인간은 원래
They are animals that gain attention by showing off their abilities.
자신의 능력을 뽐내며 주목을 받는 동물이다.
Just like every time you solve a case
사건을 해결할 때마다 그렇듯
Just call all the maids in the palace to show off?
그냥 궁궐의 시녀들을 다 불러서 자랑하라고요?
So this person is also a guy who desperately craves attention?
그럼 이 사람도 관심을 절실히 원하는 남자인 걸까요?
Are you asking a question or accusing me?
질문하는 건가요, 아니면 비난하는 건가요?
I don't dare. I'm just asking.
감히 그럴 수가 없어요. 그냥 물어보는 거야
You are forbidden to ask questions
질문하는 것은 금지되어 있습니다
I understand why you spread out these paintings.
왜 이 그림들을 퍼뜨렸는지 이해가 되네요.
Ji Tong this person
지통 이 사람
He wanted to spread the news about his theft.
그는 자신의 절도 소식을 널리 알리고 싶었습니다.
Nowadays, there are still rumors that he is a righteous thief and a big thief.
요즘에도 여전히 그가 정의로운 도둑, 큰 도둑이라는 소문이 돌고 있다.
He must be quite proud now
그 사람 지금 꽤 자랑스러울 것 같은데
Who do you think these rumors came from?
이 소문이 누구에게서 나왔다고 생각하시나요?
Could it be...
그럴 수도 있지...
It's Ji Tong
지통이에요
Immediately arrest those spreading rumors
루머 유포자 즉각 검거하라
Those lies justified his theft
그 거짓말은 그의 절도를 정당화했다
Therefore there must be criminals among them
그러므로 그들 중에는 범죄자가 있을 것이다.
Yes
예
That...sir
그게...선생님
You declare the time today
당신은 오늘 시간을 선언
Don’t you want to have tea with the concubine?
첩과 차 한잔 하고 싶지 않으세요?
Why are you saying it now?
왜 지금 그런 말을 하는 걸까요?
Didn't you just forbid me from asking questions...
방금 내가 질문하는 것을 금지하지 않았나요?
Can't you even tell the difference between "don't ask" and "don't tell"?
'묻지 마세요'와 '말하지 마세요'의 차이도 구분 못하시나요?
wake up
일어나
wake up quickly
빨리 일어나
Sir, are you back?
선생님, 돌아오셨나요?
Not who you thought he was
당신이 생각했던 그 사람이 아니야
what
뭐
Concubine
첩
Does it have to be you?
꼭 당신이어야 하나요?
Can't you just pretend to be presentable?
그냥 괜찮은 척 하면 안 되나요?
Let me think that when I come to the appointment with the king,
내가 왕과의 약속에 참석할 때,
"Our lovely Maharaja took a nap soundly."
"우리 사랑스러운 마하라자가 푹 낮잠을 잤어요."
Let me turn around and leave and come back later
돌아서서 나갔다가 나중에 다시 오도록 해주세요
This is why you stay here
이것이 당신이 여기 머무는 이유입니다
My dear, please have mercy...
사랑하는 여러분, 자비를 베풀어 주십시오...
The Lord is staring at the Maharaja eagerly.
주님은 마하라자를 간절히 바라보고 계십니다.
How can you people protect the king?
여러분은 어떻게 왕을 보호할 수 있습니까?
Send a message to my brother
동생에게 메시지를 보내세요
We need to discuss marriage for Yue'er as soon as possible
가능한 한 빨리 Yue'er의 결혼에 대해 논의해야합니다.
Yes
예
Are they planning to let Yue'er marry Da Sijian's daughter?
Yue'er가 Da Sijian의 딸과 결혼하도록 할 계획인가요?
This is also a happy event
이것도 행복한 이벤트네요
In this way
이런 식으로
Will Da Si Jian protect Lord Daoyue?
Da Si Jian은 Daoyue 경을 보호할 것인가?
Are you afraid that someone will swallow the king?
누군가가 왕을 삼킬까 두렵습니까?
The concubine is also true
첩도 맞다
This is all my fault for failing to win my stepmother's trust.
이건 모두 새엄마의 신뢰를 얻지 못한 저의 잘못입니다.
I am unethical
나는 비윤리적이다
Your Highness is serious
전하 심각하시네요
Du Chengzhi, how should I appease my stepmother?
Du Chengzhi, 계모를 어떻게 달래야합니까?
Lord Daoyue's marriage
도월공의 결혼
I have already found a family
나는 이미 가족을 찾았어요
This is a family that once served as a marshal during the Goryeo Dynasty.
고려시대 원수를 지낸 가문이다.
Just do whatever you want
그냥 하고 싶은 대로 하세요
That's my brother's marriage. You need to worry more.
그게 내 동생의 결혼이야. 더 걱정하셔야 합니다.
A family of military officers in the Goryeo Dynasty
고려시대 무신 가문
what are you doing now
지금 뭐해?
I'm afraid I'm growing rice in the mountains and forests.
산과 숲에서 벼를 재배하고 있는 게 두렵습니다.
You are really like a cunning fox
넌 정말 교활한 여우같아
If I were a fox, then who are you?
내가 여우라면 너는 누구냐?
Of course I am a nine-tailed fox
물론 나는 구미호이다
Empress of the Middle Temple
중사(中寺)의 황후
I heard that my niece is engaged to Du Chengzhi’s son?
내 조카가 Du Chengzhi의 아들과 약혼했다고 들었는데?
Yes
예
Want to use marriage to strengthen the Ren family?
Ren 가족을 강화하기 위해 결혼을 원하십니까?
Everyone knows that plan, but no one can stop it
모두가 그 계획을 알고 있지만 누구도 막을 수 없습니다
It's so heartbreaking
너무 가슴 아프네요
golden green
황금빛 녹색
Your Highness, the little girl is shy
전하, 그 어린 소녀는 수줍음이 많아요
I have repeatedly made my empress sad, and I am truly frightened.
나는 계속해서 황후를 슬프게 만들었고 정말 두렵습니다.
Please don't worry, Madam
걱정하지 마세요, 부인
Empress’ niece
황후의 조카
Dogs will treat each other with sincerity
개들은 진심을 다해 서로를 대할 것이다
Is this kind of thing worthy of being called a spring painting?
이런 것이 봄그림이라 불릴 만한 것이 있을까?
Too bland
너무 단조롭다
What a coincidence
정말 우연이군요
It seems we are destined
우리는 운명인 것 같아
what
뭐
I didn't expect to meet my fiancée here
여기서 약혼자를 만날 줄은 몰랐어요
Could it be that the young master is...
혹시 젊은 주인님이...
My father is the emperor of the current dynasty
나의 아버지는 현 왕조의 황제이다.
say hello
인사해
She is my future wife
그녀는 내 미래의 아내야
Nice to meet you. My name is Lu Yi.
만나서 반가워요. 제 이름은 루이(Lu Yi)입니다.
This is my future concubine, Mrs.
이 분은 내 미래의 첩입니다.
No. Maybe it’s already settled?
아뇨. 이미 정해져 있는 게 아닐까요?
Judging from the order of undressing, I am the main wife.
옷을 벗는 순서로 보면 내가 주부인이다.
But it’s okay to leave it to the lady.
하지만 아줌마에게 맡겨도 괜찮습니다.
It makes me happy that my wife and my concubines are getting along well with each other.
내 처와 첩들이 서로 잘 지내고 있어서 기쁘다.
Since we met by chance, how about the three of us have a drink together?
우연히 만났으니 셋이서 함께 한잔 어때요?
Anyway, we will be a family soon.
어쨌든 우리는 곧 가족이 될 거예요.
What a good idea
정말 좋은 생각이에요
Brother is still waiting for me
형은 아직도 나를 기다리고 있어
I'm going to say goodbye first
먼저 작별 인사를 할게요
Why don't you just get married without making the pretty lady cry?
그 예쁜 여자를 울리지 않고 그냥 결혼하는 게 어때요?
Marriage is a gamble
결혼은 도박이다
What I want is to double the profit. How can I say this?
내가 원하는 것은 이익을 두 배로 늘리는 것입니다. 어떻게 이것을 말할 수 있습니까?
This country has gone from king to slave
이 나라는 왕에서 노예로 바뀌었어요
Everyone relies on marriage to buy wealth, fame and power
모든 사람은 부와 명예, 권력을 얻기 위해 결혼에 의존합니다.
Seek more benefits for yourself
자신을 위해 더 많은 혜택을 찾아보세요
Then of course I have to find a bigger bet.
그러면 당연히 더 큰 내기를 찾아야 합니다.
She is the niece of the Empress of the Middle Temple
그녀는 중궁황후의 조카입니다
Is there any bigger bet than this?
이보다 더 큰 내기가 있을까요?
For example…
예를 들면…
Admiration?
감탄?
The young master is also very old-fashioned.
젊은 주인도 매우 구식입니다.
The children of high-ranking officials are all the same
고위공직자 자식은 다 똑같아
I'm just trying to look like the same old person.
나는 단지 똑같은 노인처럼 보이려고 노력하고 있습니다.
I can't live up to expectations
기대에 부응할 수 없어
wish you good health
건강을 기원합니다
uncle
삼촌
I came to get the medicinal materials I asked you for before
아까 부탁했던 약재를 구하러 왔어요
Okay, wait for me
알았어, 기다려줘
I'm back, Master
제가 돌아왔습니다, 선생님
Stop
중지
What's the matter?
무슨 일이야?
Didn't I tell you not to wear medical clothes that smell like patients?
환자 냄새 나는 의료복을 입지 말라고 하지 않았나요?
Are you in and out of the house?
집 안팎에 계십니까?
I was going to change my clothes and come back
옷 갈아입고 다시 오려고 했는데
But the Huimin Office is really busy today
그런데 오늘 희민 사무실이 너무 바빠요.
I'm just going to make some money and dare to act like a big name.
나는 단지 돈을 좀 벌고 감히 유명인처럼 행동할 것입니다.
I'm just a slave of this family
나는 이 가문의 노예일 뿐이야
So what? So what?
그래서 뭐? 그래서 뭐?
Is it reasonable for a slave to act like a celebrity?
노예가 연예인처럼 행동하는 것이 합리적입니까?
Of course it's unreasonable
물론 불합리한 일이다
That's right
그렇죠
Why are you causing trouble for me? You're so mean.
왜 나에게 문제를 일으키나요? 당신은 정말 못됐어요.
How dare you talk back to me
어떻게 감히 나한테 말대꾸를 해?
Where did the people go?
사람들은 어디로 갔나요?
Mother
어머니
When did you come back?
언제 돌아왔나요?
not long ago
얼마 전
You must be very tired. Give it to me.
많이 피곤하시겠네요. 나에게 주세요.
Look at this
이것 좀 봐
Master, these socks are so dirty
선생님, 이 양말이 너무 더러워요
Could it be that he was trying to meet a woman in the dead of night, right?
한밤중에 여자를 만나려고 했던 게 아닐까요?
How could you say such shameful things to an unmarried man?
어떻게 미혼 남자에게 그런 부끄러운 말을 할 수 있나요?
I will be responsible for drying the clothes
빨래 건조는 내가 책임질게
Just go back to your room, drink medicine and rest.
방으로 돌아가 약을 마시고 휴식을 취하세요.
Let's wash it together and then go home.
같이 씻고 집에 가자.
The medicine should be drunk while it is hot
약은 뜨거울 때 마셔야 한다
Go back quickly
빨리 돌아가라
Eunjo, please go inside.
은조 씨, 안으로 들어가세요.
Please tell me, Lord Superintendent
말해주세요, 총독님
at home
집에서
It doesn't matter if you call me daddy
날 아빠라고 불러도 상관없어
How dare I, a wicked daughter, match your father and daughter?
못된 딸인 내가 감히 너희 아버지 딸과 짝을 이룰 수 있겠느냐?
Being overheard by others can damage the reputation of the Chief Superintendent.
다른 사람이 우연히 듣는 것은 최고 교육감의 평판을 손상시킬 수 있습니다.
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
You go to Pingyan later
나중에 핑옌으로 가세요
Just wear these clothes.
그냥 이 옷을 입으세요.
Where did you get the money to buy these silk and satin clothes?
이 실크와 새틴 옷을 살 돈은 어디서 났나요?
No, not to mention...
아니, 말할 것도 없이...
Why do you need to wear silk clothes when you go to the Imperial Palace?
황궁에 갈 때 왜 비단 옷을 입어야 합니까?
You should also know
너도 알아야 해
The eldest son of that family did not take a concubine
그 집의 큰 아들은 첩을 맞이하지 않았습니다.
There should be a wedding soon
빨리 결혼식이 있어야 하는데
Forgive me for being bold. Please take back your life.
제가 대담한 것을 용서해주세요. 인생을 되찾아주세요.
I want to stay in this home forever
나는 이 집에서 영원히 머물고 싶다.
Serving Mother and the Superintendent
어머니와 교육감에게 봉사
Silly boy
바보 같은 소년
Which father wants his daughter to be alone all her life?
딸이 평생 혼자 있기를 원하는 아버지는 누구일까요?
You should also live the life of a decent woman
너도 괜찮은 여자의 삶을 살아야 해
I never intended to live my life as a woman
난 여자로 살 생각은 전혀 없었어
You have suffered enough in this family
당신은 이 가족 안에서 충분히 고통받았습니다.
It's enough
충분하다
Although you are a naughty girl
비록 당신은 못된 여자이지만
I still hope you will be treated well by that family
그래도 그 가족한테 잘 대해줬으면 좋겠어
I just gave you these
방금 이거 줬어
Just accept it and wear it
그냥 받아들이고 입으세요
I want to hold the officer responsible for the robbery
강도 사건에 대한 책임을 경찰관에게 묻고 싶습니다.
Then let’s go after the idle king first.
그럼 먼저 유휴왕을 뒤쫓자.
Let's think it's the amusement park's fault
놀이공원의 잘못이라고 생각하자
All this is for the sake of public security in the capital.
이 모든 것은 수도의 공공 안보를 위한 것입니다.
It’s for the sake of the common people and the mother-in-law.
서민과 시어머니를 위해서입니다.
No need to say much
많은 말을 할 필요가 없습니다
Don’t live for me in the future
앞으로는 나를 위해 살지마
It's time for you to settle down with a woman
이제 여자랑 화해할 시간이야
Why don't you marry Da Sijian's daughter?
Da Sijian의 딸과 결혼하는 것이 어떻습니까?
That family will be helpful to you.
그 가족이 당신에게 도움이 될 것입니다.
obey
복종하다
Do you really want to marry this person?
당신은 정말로 이 사람과 결혼하고 싶나요?
But I have to pick up the eight-character post in person.
그런데 8자 글은 제가 직접 뽑아야 해요.
What's her temperament like?
그녀의 기질은 어떤가요?
How's your bearing?
당신의 태도는 어떻습니까?
What's more important
무엇이 더 중요합니까?
I want to see with my own eyes if she is beautiful
그 사람이 아름다운지 내 눈으로 확인하고 싶어
presumptuous
주제넘은
This is not etiquette
이건 에티켓이 아니야
It seems that Ji Dong is here for this
지동이 그러려고 온 것 같다
Then he went to loot the warehouse in Da Si Jian's house.
그런 다음 그는 Da Si Jian의 집에 있는 창고를 약탈하러갔습니다.
Do you think there is a chance now?
지금이 기회라고 생각하시나요?
Have you caught the thief named "Jitong"?
'지통'이라는 도둑을 잡았나요?
I heard that he ransacked your mansion's warehouse
그 사람이 네 저택 창고를 샅샅이 뒤졌다고 들었어
I'm investigating closely
면밀히 조사하고 있어요
Your Majesty, you are so troubled
폐하, 너무 고민되세요
I feel relieved
마음이 편해진다
A sudden visit from an adult
갑자기 어른의 방문
I can only prepare some simple meals
간단한 식사만 준비할 수 있어요
Only today did I realize that the royal family’s refreshments are so simple.
왕가의 다과가 이렇게 소박하다는 것을 오늘에서야 깨달았습니다.
I took a general look at the warehouse
창고를 전체적으로 살펴봤습니다
But the real thing to see…
그런데 실물을 보니...
Only saw it now
이제서야 봤네요
she is my daughter
그 사람은 내 딸이야
Say hello to your lord quickly
빨리 주인님께 인사드려라
This is Lord Daoyue
이는 도웨경(Daoyue Lord)이다.
The little girl’s surname is “Jin” and her first name is “Zhen”
어린 소녀의 성은 '진'이고 이름은 '진'이다.
Does the word "true" mean something beautiful?
"진실"이라는 단어는 아름다운 것을 의미합니까?
yes
응
My name is Li Yue, which means "joy"
제 이름은 "기쁨"을 뜻하는 Li Yue입니다.
It seems that the two of us
아무래도 우리 둘이서
They are all worthy of their names
다들 이름값을 하는군요
Let’s go hunting together at the hunting ground some other time.
다음에 같이 사냥터로 사냥하러 가자.
I'm spoiled and I hate cruel things the most.
나는 버릇없고 잔인한 것을 가장 싫어합니다.
Beating and killing, blood splattered all over the body
때리고 죽이고, 온몸에 피가 튀었다.
Not pretty at all
전혀 예쁘지 않아
do you like hunting
당신은 사냥을 좋아합니까
How can a woman like to see blood?
여자가 어떻게 피를 보고 싶어할 수 있나요?
Bad
나쁨
If you want to be a lady of the house, you must know these things.
집안의 아주머니가 되고 싶다면 이런 것들을 알아야 합니다.
Competition and calculation are the basic equipment of the royal family.
경쟁과 계산은 왕실의 기본 장비입니다.
Your Majesty
폐하
Is it necessary to act stupid?
어리석은 행동을 할 필요가 있나요?
It will only embarrass each other
서로 당황스러울 뿐입니다
If you give birth to a great king in the future
만약 미래에 위대한 왕을 낳게 된다면
It will threaten the throne of the Crown Prince
왕세자의 왕위를 위협하게 될 것입니다.
One day in the future it may be discovered that he was poisoned to death
언젠가 그가 독살된 사실이 밝혀질 수도 있다.
Or a murder disguised as a suicide
혹은 자살을 가장한 살인
I think you should have known this for a long time
내 생각엔 당신이 이 사실을 오랫동안 알았어야 했다고 생각해요
You may also be accused of treason...
반역죄로 기소될 수도 있습니다...
What you said
당신이 말한 것
Already overstepped
이미 지나쳤어
And after that bloody storm, unfortunately...
그리고 그 피비린내 나는 폭풍 이후, 불행하게도...
I became the foundation of the country and you became the middle temple
나는 나라의 근본이 되었고 너는 중사가 되었고
You can't escape the end of being crippled either.
당신도 불구가 되는 최후를 피할 수는 없습니다.
Why do you say that?
왜 그런 말을 합니까?
Although your family is rich
집안이 부자인데도
But not a powerful house
하지만 강력한 집은 아니죠
I'm afraid it's a bit difficult to hold the nave.
본당 잡기가 좀 힘들 것 같아서요.
Then, Your Majesty...
그럼 폐하...
A king cannot be a husband
왕은 남편이 될 수 없다
The woman he wants to protect is not his own
그가 지키고 싶은 여자는 자신의 것이 아니다
But that throne
그런데 그 왕좌
Your father should know best
아버지가 가장 잘 아실 겁니다
After all, he was the one who personally deposed His Highness and his mother.
결국 그는 전하와 그의 어머니를 개인적으로 폐위시킨 사람이었습니다.
Why don't you marry Da Sijian's daughter?
Da Sijian의 딸과 결혼하는 것이 어떻습니까?
brother
형제
Didn't this kid tell me not to call me brother?
이 새끼가 나한테 형이라고 부르지 말라고 하지 않았어?
I obey the prince's residence.
나는 왕자의 거주지에 복종합니다.
But
하지만
Why can't I call you brother?
왜 형이라고 부를 수 없나요?
Because the Queen Mother is not my mother
태후는 나의 어머니가 아니기 때문이다
The abandoned concubine who was kicked out of the palace due to political struggles
정치적 갈등으로 궁궐에서 쫓겨난 버려진 후궁
She is my biological mother
그녀는 나의 생물학적 어머니이다
Yue'er, do you know what this means?
Yue'er, 이게 무슨 뜻인지 아시나요?
It means you and I are enemies
너와 내가 적이라는 뜻이야
So Yue'er
그래서 Yue'er
Don't let the world discover your cleverness
세상이 당신의 영리함을 발견하도록 두지 마십시오
Don't appear in front of me
내 앞에 나타나지 마
don't do anything
아무것도 하지 마세요
If you don't want to lose your mother like me
나처럼 엄마를 잃고 싶지 않다면
Although I couldn't keep my mother
비록 엄마를 지켜주지는 못했지만
But you have to protect the mother you left behind
하지만 두고 온 엄마를 지켜야 해
For me, getting married
나에게 있어서 결혼은
like a mouse hole
쥐구멍처럼
Do you mean to hide?
숨기겠다는 겁니까?
Try not to draw attention to yourself as much as possible
가능한 한 자신에게 관심을 끌지 마십시오.
compared to this
이것에 비해
It is best not to be seen by the concubine today...
오늘은 첩의 눈에 띄지 않는 것이 가장 좋습니다 ...
will she kill me
그 사람이 날 죽일까?
Will she kill me?
그녀가 나를 죽일 것인가?
OMG
세상에
Sir
선생님
A little fear...
약간의 두려움...
am i already dead
나 이미 죽었나요?
This smells like hell
이거 냄새가 지옥같아
Why is there a hole in Dazao?
다자오에는 왜 구멍이 있는 걸까요?
Is it for ventilation?
환기용인가요?
Because it's just a piece of shit
왜냐면 그냥 똥일 뿐이니까
What?
무엇?
This is the only piece of clothing I can borrow
내가 빌릴 수 있는 유일한 옷은 이것뿐이야
Came out in a hurry without bringing any silver.
은도 하나 가져오지 않고 서둘러 나왔다.
I can't leave here like this
이대로는 여기서 나갈 수 없어
If I'm allowed to wear this rag for more than an hour
만약 나에게 이 걸레를 한 시간 이상 착용하게 된다면
I want your life
나는 당신의 삶을 원해요
The little one will go back to the palace right away
꼬마는 곧 궁으로 돌아갈 것이다
Are you coming to see my grandfather?
할아버지를 만나러 오시나요?
Yes
예
Ever since you started taking care of your grandfather
할아버지를 돌보기 시작한 이후로
His bedsores have reduced and his complexion has improved.
욕창도 줄어들고 안색도 좋아졌습니다.
That's why my father likes you so much
그래서 우리 아빠가 널 너무 좋아하는 거야
It was the same when I was in the Huimin Administration Bureau
내가 희민관리국에 있을 때도 그랬다.
Been doing these things all the time
항상 이런 일들을 해왔어
Let’s pay a little more than the original salary.
원래 월급보다 조금 더 많이 받자.
obey
복종하다
That...sir
그게...선생님
About marriage…
결혼에 대해서…
one
하나
Which pariah dares to be so rude?
어떤 파리아가 감히 그렇게 무례하게 행동합니까?
How does this face look like a pariah?
이 얼굴은 어떻게 파리아처럼 보입니까?
Even if you are splashed with dirty water, you still exude nobility
더러운 물을 튀겨도 고귀함을 풍긴다
Wearing tattered clothes but still handsome
너덜너덜한 옷을 입었지만 여전히 잘생겼다
It's the first time I've seen this kind of guy who deserves a beating.
이렇게 때려야 할 놈은 처음 봤다.
You've been calling me guy since just now
너 방금부터 나한테 남자라고 불렀잖아
You stinky guy
냄새나는 놈아
Do you want me to teach you a lesson before you can recognize me?
당신이 나를 알아보기 전에 내가 당신에게 교훈을 주기를 원하십니까?
I think you are really crazy, right?
내 생각엔 너 정말 미친 것 같아, 그렇지?
Go to the Robbery Hall. I will punish you with regular crimes.
강도 홀로 가십시오. 나는 당신을 일반 범죄로 처벌할 것입니다.
Oh, that madman
아, 그 미친놈아
At least I'll be beaten with a hundred sticks.
적어도 나는 백 개의 막대기로 맞을 것입니다.
The crazy servant
미친 하인
If you show off your bravery, you will have no choice but to die.
용기를 과시하면 죽을 수밖에 없습니다.
come with me
나와 함께 가자
Let me go, I'll go ahead
놔줘, 내가 먼저 갈게
The Robbery Hall is a place I often go to.
강도당은 제가 자주 가는 곳이에요.
I'd be happy to show you the way
나는 당신에게 길을 보여주게 되어 기쁩니다.
It seems that you will not wake up until you die.
죽을 때까지 깨어나지 못할 것 같습니다.
Where are the people?
사람들은 어디에 있나요?
who are you?
누구세요?
young master
젊은 주인
How can you use those precious hands of yours like this?
그 소중한 손을 어떻게 이렇게 쓸 수 있지?
Isn't this person just a slave?
이 사람은 그냥 노예 아닌가요?
Servant?
하인?
It's not your turn to show up here
이제 당신이 여기 나타날 차례가 아니다
That's right. This is not something a lady should do.
맞습니다. 이건 여자가 해서는 안 되는 일이에요.
This person seems not very clear, so he makes mistakes
이 사람은 명확하지 않은 것 같아서 실수를 합니다.
Please show me your magnanimity as a gentleman.
신사로서의 관대함을 보여주세요.
A gentleman's magnanimity is not wasted on a slave like this.
이런 노예에게는 신사의 관대함이 낭비되지 않습니다.
The slaves plowed the fields and harvested rice
노예들은 밭을 갈고 쌀을 수확했습니다.
How can you wear such good clothes?
어떻게 이렇게 좋은 옷을 입을 수 있나요?
He's tall and strong, and he looks good, right?
그 사람은 키도 크고 힘도 세고 보기에도 좋죠?
That's it. Let's talk about it
그게 다야. 그것에 대해 이야기하자
if kill him
그를 죽이면
Who will raise the cows?
소는 누가 키울 것인가?
Is he a slave of a lady's family?
그는 여자 가족의 노예입니까?
Lady?
숙녀?
Ah, he is talking about me
아, 그 사람이 내 얘기를 하는구나
That's right
그렇죠
he is my servant
그는 내 하인이다
Who? Me?
누구? 나?
After our grandfather passed away, our family
할아버지가 돌아가신 후 우리 가족은
The family fell into ruin overnight
가족은 하룻밤 사이에 파멸했다
Every slave is precious
모든 노예는 소중하다
But after he fell from the pear tree
하지만 배나무에서 떨어진 후
Just completely crazy
그냥 완전 미쳤어
That's why I need to take care of him like this
그래서 내가 그 사람을 이렇게 돌봐야 해요.
Thank you so much for your hard work
여러분의 노고에 정말 감사드립니다.
rude
무례한
If you want to punish me, punish me.
나를 처벌하고 싶다면 나를 처벌하십시오.
There's no need for this
이럴 필요는 없어
Of course it doesn't need to be like this
물론 꼭 이럴 필요는 없지
Don’t bow your head easily without permission
허락 없이 쉽게 고개를 숙이지 마세요
If you bow your head for me, then don’t do this even more
나한테 고개 숙인다면 더 이상 이러지 마
No one dares to punish me rashly
아무도 감히 나를 함부로 처벌하지 못한다
And I'm definitely not anyone's slave...
그리고 난 누구의 노예도 아닌데...
Why are my knees on the ground?
내 무릎은 왜 땅에 닿아 있나요?
Who put my knees on the ground
누가 내 무릎을 땅에 대고
Did you make me kneel down?
나를 무릎 꿇게 한 거야?
Look, I'm from this country...
보세요, 저는 이 나라 출신이에요...
No, he started a few days ago
아니요, 며칠 전에 시작했어요
He kept saying that he was possessed by the ghost general
자신이 귀신장수에 홀렸다고 계속 말하더군요
Making a lot of noise all day long
하루종일 시끄럽게 떠들고
Be quiet…
조용히 하세요…
Is he really a slave of a lady's family?
그는 정말로 여자 가족의 노예입니까?
Yes
예
He is my slave, yes
그 사람은 내 노예야, 그래
My servant girl...
내 하인이여...
Girl? Girl?
여자? 소녀?
boy
소년
I mean boy
내 말은, 소년
"Boy"
"소년"
"Boy"?
"소년"?
Hello Seungbaek
안녕하세요 승백님
Master?
선생님?
If I'm discovered to be a slave, it'll be over
노예로 밝혀지면 끝장이야
Then I'll take it as forgiven and take the first step.
그러면 용서받은 것으로 받아들이고 첫발을 내딛겠습니다.
let me go
날 보내줘
I don't want to make you regret more
더 이상 후회하게 만들고 싶지 않아
Please, do you want me to be beaten to death with a stick together with you?
제발, 나도 당신과 함께 막대기로 맞아 죽기를 원하십니까?
Will you die? Yes, let’s go quickly
당신은 죽을 것인가? 응, 빨리 가자
What are you arguing about?
당신은 무엇에 대해 논쟁하고 있습니까?
I've never seen that kind of madman
난 그런 미친놈을 본 적이 없어
Her back looks familiar
그녀의 뒷모습은 낯익어 보인다
let me go
날 보내줘
They don't seem to be chasing me
그 사람들이 날 쫓는 것 같지는 않은데
why are you running away
왜 도망치는 거야?
Because my young master...
왜냐면 내 어린 주인님...
Having said that
그렇게 말하면서
Why are you so arrogant after I saved you?
내가 당신을 구한 뒤에 당신은 왜 그렇게 오만합니까?
I spared the other person's life
나는 다른 사람의 생명을 구했다
Oh my god
맙소사
It seems you didn't pretend to be crazy or stupid on purpose.
일부러 미친 척, 멍청한 척 한 건 아닌 것 같아요.
Are you pretending to be crazy?
미친 척 하는 거야?
You're not trying to reduce the usual sins
당신은 평소의 죄를 줄이려고 노력하는 것이 아닙니다
Are you deliberately pretending to be mentally disturbed?
일부러 정신적으로 불안한 척 하는 건가요?
No one in that market could punish me for ordinary crimes.
그 시장의 어느 누구도 일반적인 범죄로 나를 처벌할 수 없습니다.
He's quite crazy
그 사람 완전 미쳤어
I can't believe I look like this either
나도 내가 이렇게 생겼다니 믿을 수가 없어
But I refuse to explain any more
하지만 더 이상 설명을 거부합니다
I also refuse to meddle in other people's business.
나는 또한 다른 사람의 일에 간섭하는 것을 거부합니다.
Goodbye
안녕
You need to speak clearly first
먼저 명확하게 말해야 해요
What did you mean when you said that even you would be beaten to death with a stick?
당신도 몽둥이로 맞아 죽는다는 말은 무슨 뜻입니까?
I came here with you because of those words
그 말 때문에 너와 함께 여기까지 왔어
you have to explain it to me
나한테 설명해줘야 해
What else could it mean?
또 무슨 뜻일까요?
If the lies are revealed, both of us will be sentenced...
만약 거짓말이 밝혀지면 우리 둘 다 처벌을 받게 될 거에요...
If I say now that we are both slaves
지금 우리 둘 다 노예라고 말하면
He will definitely be even more angry
그 사람은 분명 더 화를 낼 거야.
Aren't you my slave?
당신은 내 노예가 아닌가요?
I mean, I'd be held accountable for lying too.
거짓말한 것에 대해서도 책임을 져야 한다는 뜻이다.
So why do you have to stand up for others casually?
그렇다면 왜 아무렇지도 않게 남의 편에 서서 일어서야 합니까?
What do you think about the situation just now?
지금 상황에 대해 어떻게 생각하시나요?
Will it be over as long as you get a spanking?
때리기만 하면 끝나나요?
your parents
너의 부모님
Even distant relatives may be implicated.
먼 친척이라도 연루될 수 있습니다.
You are really nosy
너 정말 참견쟁이야
I know it too
나도 알아
Although God has not given me anything
신이 나에게 아무것도 주지 않았지만
But one of them is nosy
그런데 그 중 하나가 코가 심해요
I'm tired too
나도 피곤해
What are the remaining items?
남은 품목은 무엇인가요?
Poverty, shabbyness, downfall, tears
가난, 초라함, 몰락, 눈물
Fortunately, amid these misfortunes
다행히도 이러한 불행 속에서도
And my mother is by my side
그리고 엄마는 내 옆에 있어
And...father
그리고...아버지
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
Why is he looking at me like that?
그 사람은 왜 나를 그렇게 쳐다보는 걸까?
Don't answer him anymore. Let's go.
더 이상 그 사람에게 대답하지 마세요. 갑시다.
Then I'll take my leave first.
그럼 먼저 이만 물러가겠습니다.
my satin clothes
내 새틴 옷
Don't get caught in the rain
비를 맞지 마세요
Are you very athletic?
당신은 운동 능력이 뛰어나나요?
I have never been exposed to rain since I was born
나는 태어나서 한번도 비를 맞아본 적이 없다.
You may not believe it, but it is true
믿기지 않으실 수도 있지만 사실입니다
yes
응
If I get cold
내가 추워지면
There are more than one or two medical officers who have been questioned.
조사를 받은 의료진은 한두 명 이상이다.
You probably don’t believe this either, but it’s true
아마 당신도 이것을 믿지 않을 것입니다. 그러나 그것은 사실입니다
yes
응
Don't you believe it?
믿을 수 없나요?
Yes
예
what are you doing
뭐하는거야?
Mud water will splash up.
흙탕물이 튀게 됩니다.
This is my first pair of embroidered shoes and satin clothes
이건 내 첫 번째 자수 신발과 새틴 옷이야
How poor is your family?
당신의 가족은 얼마나 가난합니까?
Even so, how can a lady reveal her bare feet so easily?
그런데 어떻게 여자가 맨발을 그렇게 쉽게 드러낼 수 있지?
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
what are you doing
뭐하는거야?
You've never been in the rain, so you don't know
넌 비를 맞아본 적이 없어서 모르지
when the raindrops fall on you
빗방울이 너에게 떨어지면
The depression in my heart seems to be diluted a little.
마음속의 우울함이 조금은 희석되는 것 같습니다.
How is it possible
어떻게 가능합니까?
I mean it
진심이야
But you probably don’t believe it either, right?
하지만 아마 당신도 믿지 않을 겁니다. 그렇죠?
Are you sure it was rain hitting my back?
비가 내 등을 때린 게 확실해요?
I always feel like I've been struck by lightning
나는 항상 번개를 맞은 것 같은 기분이 든다.
Why was your mouth the only one not struck by lightning?
왜 당신의 입만 번개에 맞지 않았습니까?
It's really...too cold
정말...너무 추워요
I can't move
움직일 수가 없어
Take off your clothes
옷을 벗으세요
Stop playing tricks over there
거기서 장난 그만 치세요
Squeeze out the water
물을 짜내세요
The clothes can be dried faster
옷이 더 빨리 건조될 수 있어요
Just a little rain
비가 조금 내렸어요
Just make a fuss over there
그냥 거기서 소란을 피우세요
My body touched cold water for the first time
내 몸이 처음으로 차가운 물에 닿았어
I have always been exposed to hot water with floral scent
나는 항상 꽃향기가 나는 뜨거운 물에 노출되어 왔습니다.
So who told you to come over here?
그럼 누가 여기로 오라고 했나요?
Didn't you say this is the only satin dress?
이게 유일한 새틴 드레스라고 하지 않았나요?
God has not given you anything
신은 너에게 아무것도 주지 않았어
Wouldn't it be too painful if you were still exposed to the rain?
아직도 비를 맞고 있다면 너무 고통스럽지 않을까요?
That…
그…
thank you
감사합니다
This is more than just a thank you, it should be a holy grace...
이건 단순한 감사를 넘어 거룩한 은혜여야 하는데...
Hello
안녕하세요
Do you see anyone sitting here?
여기 앉아 있는 사람이 보이나요?
Too bad
안타깝다
What adults hate the most is rain.
어른들이 가장 싫어하는 것은 비다.
Don't you know how to tie it?
묶는 방법을 모르시나요?
My hands are not for tying clothes
내 손은 옷을 묶는 손이 아니다
I have never been exposed to rain in my life.
나는 살면서 비를 맞아본 적이 없습니다.
I haven't tied my clothes yet
아직 옷을 묶지 않았어
what on earth have you done
도대체 무슨 짓을 한 거야?
I mainly play
주로 놀아요
This is my most important job
이것이 나의 가장 중요한 일이다
Well, play until you go crazy
자, 미칠 때까지 놀아라
Looks like it won't rain again
다시는 비가 안 올 것 같아
No need
필요 없음
This is what I want to throw away
버리고 싶은 건 바로 이것
I don't like to encounter something that looks strange.
I don't like to encounter something that looks strange.
Something uncomfortable
뭔가 불편하다
he is crazy
그는 미쳤어
Stop talking to him
그 사람이랑 얘기 좀 그만해
Since you want to throw it away, I will pick it up.
버리시겠다니까 제가 주울게요.
What is your father's name?
아버지의 이름은 무엇입니까?
Even if the family falls into decline, the family will still exist.
가족이 쇠퇴하더라도 가족은 계속 존재합니다.
tell me
말해봐
Do you want to tell the truth now?
이제 진실을 말하고 싶나요?
Tell him I'm a slave like him
나도 그 사람과 같은 노예라고 전해줘
Her face became very stiff
얼굴이 많이 굳어졌는데
Is it a family that was wiped out?
전멸당한 가족인가요?
If it's hard to say, forget it
말하기 힘들다면 잊어버리세요
But
하지만
Come to Xiaoxia Valley on the day of the full moon at You hour
보름달이 뜨는 날 당신의 시간에 Xiaoxia Valley로 오세요
why should i do this
내가 왜 이걸 해야 해?
For your meddling, I'm going to reward you handsomely.
당신의 간섭에 대해, 나는 당신에게 아낌없이 보상할 것입니다.
These shoes are enough
이 신발이면 충분해요
Then be careful on the road
그럼 길 조심하세요
I think it's not enough
내 생각엔 충분하지 않은 것 같아
and i
그리고 나
I want to see you again
다시 보고 싶어
Be sure to come
꼭 오세요
I understand
나는 이해한다
What kind of reward are you talking about?
어떤 종류의 보상을 말하는 건가요?
Payback?
회수?
I want to punish you for treating me like a slave
나를 노예 취급한 널 벌주고 싶어
Sir, you are here
선생님, 여기 계세요
You've been here for more than an hour
당신은 여기에 한 시간 넘게 있었어요
father
아버지
Well, come in
자, 들어와
Is Eunjo getting married?
은조는 결혼해요?
Won’t the family earn less money this way?
이렇게 하면 가족이 돈을 덜 벌지 않을까요?
We are already very poor
우리는 이미 너무 가난해요
Stop talking
그만 얘기해
I heard that you also bought her some satin clothes
그녀에게 새틴 옷도 사줬다고 들었어
Where did that money come from?
그 돈은 어디서 났나요?
I bought it with the money Eunjo earned during this period.
그동안 은조가 번 돈으로 샀어요.
I'll sell that satin dress right away
그 새틴 드레스 당장 팔게요
The money earned by this slave is my money, right?
이 노예가 번 돈은 내 돈 맞죠?
go out
나가다
Don't let Eunjo get married
은조 결혼 못하게 해
I told you to stand down
내가 물러나라고 했잖아
sorry
미안
I hope the engagement can be postponed a little bit
결혼은 좀 미뤄졌으면 좋겠다
I also need to take care of my sick mother
아픈 엄마도 돌봐야 해요
after that incident
그 사건 이후
Life is still not rich
인생은 아직 풍요롭지 못하다
I can't even cope with the money I make.
버는 돈도 감당할 수가 없어요.
I see what you mean
무슨 말인지 알겠다
But Grandpa doesn't have much time left
그런데 할아버지에겐 시간이 별로 없어요
What?
무엇?
Are you talking about the great master?
위대한 스승님을 말씀하시는 건가요?
father said
아버지가 말씀하셨다
As a child, we cannot let our grandfather die alone.
어렸을 때 우리는 할아버지를 혼자 죽게 할 수 없습니다.
So I plan to let you stay and serve me and take you as my concubine.
그래서 나는 당신을 머물게 하여 나를 섬기고 당신을 내 첩으로 삼을 계획입니다.
Is the person I want to marry the eldest man?
내가 결혼하고 싶은 사람은 장남인가?
Why do you look so unwilling?
왜 그렇게 의지가 없어 보이나요?
Not so
그렇지 않다
small fear
작은 두려움
If you dare to make that expression again
감히 또 그런 표정을 짓는다면
I will kick out all your family members living in that house.
그 집에 사는 너희 식구들을 다 쫓아내겠다.
You should be lucky that your father and my father are old friends
네 아버지와 내 아버지가 오랜 친구라는 건 행운이겠지
I am different from my father
나는 아버지와 다르다
If it were me, on the day of the disaster that happened in the Gengwu year
만약 나라면 경무년에 재난이 일어났던 날
I will kill them all together with all the mice in your house.
내가 너희 집에 있는 모든 쥐와 함께 그들을 다 죽이리라.
calm down
진정해
This wedding has to happen anyway
어쨌든 이 결혼식은 이뤄져야 해
In North Korea, marriage is a transaction
북한에서는 결혼이 거래다.
No matter it is a powerful king
아무리 강력한 왕이라도
Or a naughty girl like me
아니면 나처럼 못된 여자
So I have to calculate carefully
그래서 잘 계산해야해요
one
하나
Lord Superintendent?
주 교육감?
Are you saying that it’s less than one or two?
한두개 미만이라는 말씀이신가요?
I spent ten whole nights copying it.
나는 그것을 복사하는 데 열흘 밤을 보냈습니다.
That…
그…
Because there are too many typos in these four volumes
이 4권은 오타가 너무 많아서
That's it
그게 다야
I'm older
나는 나이가 많다
All dazzled
모두 눈부시게
Then get rid of these rolls and pay me.
그럼 이 두루마리를 치우고 나에게 돈을 주세요.
Sorry, I can only give you these
죄송합니다. 이것만 드릴 수 있어요
don't say that
그런 말 하지 마
Thank you for your hard work
당신의 노고에 감사드립니다
that
그
I want to ask one thing
한 가지 묻고 싶습니다.
The one who just left
방금 떠난 사람
When did you start copying?
언제부터 복사를 시작하셨나요?
About a year ago
약 1년 전
It actually... lasted for a year?
사실... 1년 정도 지속됐나요?
This is effective for relieving coughs. Let's fry it and drink it.
이는 기침 완화에 효과적입니다. 볶아서 마시자.
How could I accept such a valuable thing?
내가 어떻게 이런 귀한 것을 받아들일 수 있겠는가?
That is Superintendent Hong Minzhi
바로 홍민지 교육감입니다.
Because of his outspoken advice to the king,
그가 왕에게 솔직하게 조언한 것 때문에,
Only then was he involved in the disaster of the Gengwu period
그제서야 그는 경무시대의 재난에 연루되었다.
resulting in loss of official position
그로 인해 공식적인 지위를 상실하게 됨
All the property was confiscated
재산은 모두 압수됐다.
Lord Superintendent, I am Eunjo
총경님, 저는 은조입니다
Well, come in
자, 들어와
Did you just come back from Pingyan's house?
방금 Pingyan의 집에서 돌아오셨나요?
So beautiful
너무 아름다워
That Mr. Superintendent
그 교육감님
May I ask the person who wants to be my husband...
남편이 되고 싶은 사람에게 물어봐도 될까요...
Do you mean carrying?
가지고 다니라는 말인가요?
What happened to him
그에게 무슨 일이 일어났는가
As expected, my father didn’t know that the person I was marrying was the eldest man.
역시 아버지는 내가 결혼하는 사람이 장남이라는 사실을 모르고 계셨다.
I'm afraid he didn't expect it to be the eldest master at all
유감스럽게도 그는 그것이 가장 나이 많은 주인이 될 것이라고 전혀 기대하지 않았습니다.
nothing
아무것도
I heard that he is still living under someone else’s roof
그 사람 아직도 다른 집에 살고 있다고 들었어
How could the highly respected Yangban end up like this?
존경받는 양반이 어찌하여 이렇게 될 수 있었는가?
If you dare to make that expression again
감히 또 그런 표정을 짓는다면
I'll put your family in that house
내가 그 집에 네 가족을 넣어줄게
Drive them all out
다 몰아내세요
Your Majesty
폐하
Come in
들어와
There's a message from the Robbery Bureau
강도국에서 메시지가 왔습니다
It seems that we have found traces of Ji Dong
지동의 흔적을 찾은 것 같아요
Ji Tong?
지통?
I don't know
모르겠어요
Just heard other people mention it
방금 다른 사람들이 언급하는 걸 들었어
If you don't admit who told you
누가 말했는지 인정하지 않는다면
I can punish you as a criminal
당신을 범죄자로 처벌할 수 있어요
what
뭐
Sir, you are also true
선생님, 당신도 사실이에요
How can this be so
어떻게 이럴 수가 있지?
She's even just a widow with children
그녀는 심지어 아이들이 있는 과부일 뿐이에요
I'm just saying
난 그냥 말하는거야
I did see Ji Tong that night when I was little
나는 어렸을 때 밤에 Ji Tong을 보았습니다.
Seeing him flying over the walls
그가 벽 너머로 날아가는 걸 보고
Not this person. You can even see the tiger in front of you as a pig.
이 사람은 아닙니다. 눈앞에 호랑이가 돼지로 변해 있는 모습도 볼 수 있다.
What can be seen
볼 수 있는 것
What did you say?
뭐라고 했어?
Stop exaggerating and tell the truth quickly.
과장하지 말고 빨리 진실을 말하세요.
It's indeed Bai Ding
정말 바이딩이군요
what is that
그게 뭐야?
Even though it’s late at night, I’m sure I saw it right
늦은 밤인데도 분명 제대로 봤을 거야
He's wearing a Baiding mask?
바이딩 마스크를 쓰고 있다고요?
Let's go
가자
Wait for me
나를 기다려요
Can we really let that widow go?
정말 그 과부를 놓아줄 수 있을까요?
I let her go on purpose
난 일부러 그녀를 놓아줬어
Even though it’s late at night, I’m sure I saw it right
늦은 밤인데도 분명 제대로 봤을 거야
You can even see the tiger in front of you as a pig
눈앞에 호랑이가 돼지로 변해 있는 모습도 볼 수 있다
What can be seen
볼 수 있는 것
They cleverly concealed Ji Tong's whereabouts
그들은 지통의 행방을 교묘하게 숨겼습니다.
They definitely know him
그 사람들은 확실히 그를 알아요
What did I say to you?
내가 당신에게 뭐라고 말했습니까?
Don't use that mouth randomly
그 입을 함부로 사용하지 마세요
Hey, who am I saying that for?
내가 누구를 위해 그런 말을 하는 거지?
Just say wait until I leave together
그냥 내가 같이 갈 때까지 기다리라고 해
Draw a picture of Ji Tong and spy on the widow
Ji Tong의 그림을 그리고 과부를 염탐하세요
Wherever she touches there will be a lucky boy
그녀가 닿는 곳마다 행운의 소년이 있을 거야
Yes
예
Are you going to enter the palace then?
그럼 궁에 들어갈 건가요?
I have an appointment today
오늘 약속이 있어요
Be sure to come
꼭 오세요
I understand
나는 이해한다
It's time to show her some color
이제 그녀에게 색깔을 보여줄 시간이에요
Eunjo, I'm sorry, I'm late.
은조 씨, 미안해요, 늦어서요.
I suddenly have something urgent to deal with
갑자기 급한 일이 생겨서
Come
오세요
The child just fell asleep
아이가 방금 잠들었어요
thank you
감사합니다
I'll find you later in the evening
이따 저녁에 찾아갈게요
There is something urgent to do now
지금 급하게 해야 할 일이 있어요
OK go ahead
알았어 계속해
Are you well, your lord?
잘 계시나요, 영주님?
It's Eunjo
은조예요
I have something to say to you
당신에게 할 말이 있어요
Lord Superintendent
주 교육감
Please come out and have a look
꼭 나오셔서 구경해주세요
These are the wedding gifts they sent to Enzu
엔즈에게 보낸 결혼선물들이에요
Are these all gifts from Pingyan?
이게 다 핑옌이 준 선물인가요?
Yes
예
Don't let anyone touch these items
누구도 이 물건을 만지지 못하게 하세요
Just keep it organized
그냥 정리해서 보관하세요
I will spot the opportunity
나는 기회를 포착할 것이다
Ask you to hold a wedding
결혼식을 올려달라고 하세요
Your Majesty, the wedding gifts have been delivered successfully.
폐하, 결혼 선물이 성공적으로 전달되었습니다.
OK Got it
알았어 알았어
Our Lord Superintendent
우리 주님 교육감
Didn't know that I was going to marry Lord Dalingjian
내가 Dalingjian 경과 결혼하게 될 줄은 몰랐어요
It seems that the host completely misunderstood what I said.
진행자가 내 말을 완전히 오해한 것 같습니다.
Although I value you as an evil girl
난 너를 나쁜 여자로 소중히 여기지만
You are a precious daughter to him.
당신은 그 사람에게 소중한 딸입니다.
Just a slave to me
나한테는 노예일 뿐이야
Then please continue to let him misunderstand
그럼 계속 오해하게 해주세요
I hope before the wedding
결혼식 전에는 좋겠다
Can make my family think that I will become the eldest master's concubine
우리 가족이 내가 큰 주인의 첩이 될 것이라고 생각하게 만들 수 있습니까?
why should i do that
내가 왜 그걸 해야 해?
Because our chief supervisor
왜냐하면 우리의 수석 감독관이
Not that bad of a father
그렇게 나쁜 아버지는 아니야
Will marry her daughter to a widower over seventy years old
그녀의 딸을 일흔이 넘은 홀아비와 결혼할 것이다
You also know his character, right?
너도 그 사람 성격 알지?
In addition
게다가
If it weren’t for the incident in the Gengwu Year, my father would
경오년 사건이 아니었다면 우리 아버지는
We ended up like this today
오늘 우리는 이렇게 됐어
Would you still make such a request now?
지금도 그런 요청을 하시겠습니까?
After all, he once served as a military judge
결국 그는 한때 군사 판사를 역임했습니다.
Do you think I have humiliated your father?
내가 네 아버지를 모욕했다고 생각하니?
Okay, keep talking
알았어, 계속 얘기해
Please say this marriage was requested by me
이 결혼은 내가 요청했다고 말해주세요
Because I want to eat well and sleep well in a powerful house
힘센 집에서 잘 먹고 잘 자고 싶으니까
That's human nature
그게 인간의 본성이에요
Your filial piety is so admirable
당신의 효심은 정말 존경스럽습니다
Not as good as you, the Commander-in-Chief
너만큼은 안돼, 총사령관
My father will be bedridden for the rest of his life
아버지는 평생 침대에 누워 계실 거예요
This means
이는 다음을 의미합니다.
You can't live your whole life as a woman
평생을 여자로 살 수는 없다
But do you care more about your father being sad?
하지만 당신은 아버지가 슬퍼하는 것에 더 관심이 있습니까?
It was me who said that I would serve my parents for the rest of my life.
평생 부모님을 섬기겠다고 한 건 나였다.
Even if I can't live as a woman
여자로 살 수는 없어도
I won't feel pity either
나도 불쌍하지 않을 거야
Why don't you refuse me with this momentum?
이 기세로 나를 거절하는 게 어때?
When all our family property was confiscated
우리 가족의 재산이 모두 몰수되었을 때
It was you who took our family in
우리 가족을 데려간 건 너였어
and continue to help us keep our homes.
그리고 우리가 집을 지킬 수 있도록 계속 도와주세요.
I'm glad that I can repay your kindness in this way
이렇게 은혜에 보답할 수 있어서 기뻐요
Consider it the value of your filial piety.
그것을 효도의 가치로 여기십시오.
Smart children are born as concubines
똑똑한 아이들은 첩으로 태어납니다
The beneficiary must be deeply regretful.
수혜자는 깊이 반성해야 합니다.
I didn't lose out on this deal.
나는 이 거래에서 패하지 않았다.
First, I guarded the Chief Superintendent and his family.
먼저 총감과 그 가족을 지켰습니다.
Second, I let my mother live a good life
둘째, 어머니가 착하게 살게 해주세요
Third, I even married into a powerful family
셋째, 유력 가문에 시집도 갔습니다
Fourth, my God, I even have adult children and grandchildren.
넷째, 맙소사, 나에게는 성인 자녀와 손주까지 있습니다.
Fifth, plus the person who will become my husband...
다섯째, 게다가 내 남편이 될 사람...
Enzu
엔즈
I will take good care of your mother
내가 네 엄마를 잘 돌봐줄게
Don't worry
걱정하지 마세요
Live your life as a woman
여자로서 인생을 살아라
Make love with your husband to the fullest
남편과 최대한 사랑을 나누십시오.
Any wedding in North Korea
북한의 모든 결혼식
I won't trade my love for you
나는 당신을 위해 내 사랑을 바꾸지 않을 것입니다
Especially for a slave like me
특히 나 같은 노예에게는
People say they feel uneasy before a wedding.
사람들은 결혼식을 앞두고 불안하다고 합니다.
Is that why?
그 이유는 무엇입니까?
This means
이는 다음을 의미합니다.
You can't live your whole life as a woman
평생을 여자로 살 수는 없다
What? Do you feel pity now?
무엇? 지금 불쌍하다고 느끼시나요?
I came here without realizing it
나도 모르게 여기까지 왔는데
Why is that person here?
그 사람이 왜 여기에 있는 걸까요?
Come to Xiaoxia Valley on the day of the full moon at You hour
보름달이 뜨는 날 당신의 시간에 Xiaoxia Valley로 오세요
Is it today?
오늘인가요?
Did he wait until now?
그 사람 지금까지 기다렸나요?
Then why did I come here?
그럼 나는 왜 여기에 왔는가?
How strange
얼마나 이상한가
It happens to be today
오늘이 되는군요
It just so happens that…
어쩌다보니 그런 일이...
now
지금
that person
그 사람
If I can no longer live as a woman in the future
만약 내가 앞으로 더 이상 여자로 살 수 없다면
If tonight might be the last
오늘 밤이 마지막일지도 모른다면
Why did you come now?
왜 지금 왔나요?
Do you know how long I have been waiting for you...
내가 얼마나 오랫동안 당신을 기다렸는지 아세요?
This…
이…
Let's consider this as compensation.
이것을 보상이라고 생각해보자.
Sir
선생님
Sir, why is your face so red?
선생님, 얼굴이 왜 이렇게 빨개지세요?
I just...
난 그냥...
Something was stolen
물건을 도난당했어요
What did the other party steal?
상대방은 무엇을 훔쳤나요?
That…
그…
what happened to me
나에게 무슨 일이 일어났는가
I'm really crazy
나 정말 미쳤어
How do you plan to bear the consequences?
그 결과를 어떻게 감당할 계획인가요?
Where have you gone?
어디 갔어?
It's already so late. I won't be able to catch up.
이미 너무 늦었어요. 나는 따라잡을 수 없을 것이다.
It’s time for people to close the gates of the capital
이제 사람들이 수도의 문을 닫을 시간이다
Please forgive me for the crazy thing I did today
오늘 내가 미친 짓을 한 것을 용서해주세요
and the business I will now mind
그리고 지금 내가 신경 쓸 일은
Did you miss it?
놓치셨나요?
I…
나는…
I'll definitely catch you
꼭 잡아줄게
It's extraordinarily tight today.
오늘은 유난히 빡빡합니다.
I heard that the holder of Bai Dong's mask is Ji Dong
바이동 가면의 주인이 지동이라고 들었는데
If a woman takes the initiative to kiss
여자가 먼저 키스를 하면
Probably just admiration
아마 그저 감탄일 것이다.
The appearance of a man is indeed attractive enough
남자의 외모는 정말 충분히 매력적이다
We must find her
우리는 그녀를 찾아야 해요
Has anyone seen this woman?
이 여자 본 사람 있나요?
Why do you have to do this?
왜 이런 일을 해야 합니까?
Even a wicked girl dares to protect her brother as a sister
사악한 소녀조차도 감히 동생을 자매로서 보호합니다.
really unpleasant
정말 불쾌하다
He said he saw a suspicious person
수상한 사람을 봤다고 하더군요
Are you going to the warehouse of Da Si Jian's family?
Da Si Jian 가족의 창고에 가시나요?
Found Ji Tong
지통을 찾았습니다